Guide to the Halcyon Literary Club Records, 1910-2011 RL.00492
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Halcyon Literary Club records
1910-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Halcyon Literary Club
RL.00492
4.0 Linear Feet
5.02 Gigabytes
Durham, N.C., club organized "to promote interest in literary study and to further social enjoyment." Limited to thirty female members. Collection includes club history research, program booklets for the length of the club's operation, various correspondence from club members, meeting minutes, and historical versions of the constitution and other administrative materials.
3000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Halcyon Literary Club Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1975, 2012, and 2016.
Historical Note
The Halcyon Literary Club was formed among 12 women in Durham in 1910 "to promote interest in literary study and to further social enjoyment." Club histories reveal that early meetings were held once a month, with a luncheon followed by a book club. An annual theme was selected by the Club's program committee. Topics ranged, based on the interests of the Club's members, and included several countries or regions, art, music, as well as different genres of literature, including North Carolina authors, humorists, drama, and novels. Several mid-century programs discussed the changing roles of women in society. Membership grew but was capped at 30 members, excluding daughters or daughters-in-law.
Along with monthly meetings, the Club has maintained an active outreach program, beginning by contributing generously to charities in Europe following World War II. Recent efforts have focused locally on the Durham County Public Library, various symphonies, and local arts councils.
Collection Overview
The collection has been arranged into four series: Club History, Halcyon Members, Programs, and Club Administration. The Club History Series contains research and recollections by Halcyon members about the group's founding and early members. A large portion of this series is the Centennial Memory Notebook, created in 2011 in honor of the Halcyon Club's 100th anniversary. The series also includes handwritten and typed histories by club members from the 1930s through the 1990s. The Halcyon Members Series includes membership and officer lists, news coverage, membership nomination letters, resignation letters, and other correspondence between members relating to Halcyon member business. The majority of the Programs Series consists of the Halcyon Literary Club program booklets, created each year with the annual theme, schedule, and lists of participating and hosting members. Some years include multiple copies of the program booklets, sometimes including members' personalized notes. Other materials in the series include written book reviews, essays, and poems from different prgrams throughout the Club's history. Finally, the Club Administration Series includes meeting minutes, copies of the constitution, financial records, and receipts from various charitable donations made by Halcyon. This series also includes notes from families across the world thanking the Halcyon Club for contributing Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe (C.A.R.E.) packages during the post-World War II period. Thematic summaries of the meeting minutes have been collected by Halcyon members and are included in the Club History Series.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Literature -- Societies, etc.; Clubs -- North Carolina -- Durham; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Women -- Societies and clubs; Machine-readable artifacts; Halcyon Literary Club
- Club History Series, 1931-2011
  Scope and Contents note
  The collection has been arranged into four series: Club History, Halcyon Members, Programs, and Club Administration. The Club History Series contains research and recollections by Halcyon members about the group's founding and early members. A large portion of this series is the Centennial Memory Notebook, created in 2011 in honor of the Halcyon Club's 100th anniversary. The series also includes handwritten and typed histories by club members from the 1930s through the 1990s.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
  - Centennial Memory Notebook, 2011; 8 folders (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes cover and introduction, programs, list of program topics, histories, membership list (1910-2011), "Halcyons in the News," and profiles.
  - Club History, by Mrs. C.C. Thomas, 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - "Lest We Forget," Club History, by Mrs. Helen Davis, 1931-1952 (Box 1)
  - History of Halcyon, by Hatsy Moorhead, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Notes from Minutes, 7 folders (Box 1)
    Includes research on early members and notes written by Lucy Grant. Topics covererd by Grant include meeting locations outside homes, Halcyon programs, Halcyon people and homes, asides, Halcyon food, and outside speakers.
  - Research on founding members (Box 1)
  - Member biographies, by Lola Williams (Box 1)
  - Profiles of former members' husbands (Box 8)
  - Halcyon Archive Inventory (Box 8)
  - Arrowhead Inn tour recording, 2010; 1 CD containing 1 audio file, 22.7 MB (Digital-materials RL00492-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 1)
    Audio file in WMA format
  - Halcyon house photographs, 2008-2010; 1 DVD containing 48 files, 30.2 MB (Digital-materials RL00492-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 1)
    48 photographs in JPG format
  - Halcyon house slideshows, 2010; 2 DVDs, 4.63 GB (Digital-materials RL00492-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 1)
- Halcyon Members, 1910-2011
  This series includes membership and officer lists, news coverage, nomination letters, resignation letters, and other correspondence between members relating to Halcyon member business.
  - Membership lists, officers, and duties (Box 2)
  - Halcyons in the news, 1910-2011 (Box 2, Box 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, obituaries, sympathy notes, 1923-2011 (Box 2, Box 8)
  - Nomination letters, 1972-2000 and undated (Box 2)
  - Nomination letters, 2008-2010 (Box 8)
  - Acceptance letters, 1919 and 1979-1981 (Box 2)
  - Thank you notes and acknowledgements, 1923-1972 (Box 2)
  - Thank you notes and acknowledgements, 2010-2011 (Box 8)
  - Resignation letters, 1969-1996 and undated (Box 2)
  - Other member letters, 1979-1996 (Box 2)
  - Members' homes (Box 8)
  - Founding members (Box 8)
  - Historic membership (Box 8)
  - Member photographs, 2008 (Box 8)
  - Member interviews, member profiles, membership rosters (Box 8)
  - Books by Halcyon members and featuring Halcyon Literary Club (Box 9)
    Includes book by Duke alumna Ann Dodds Costello with a profile of Halcyon Book Club, "Smart Women: The Search for America's Historic All-Women Study Clubs". Also includes books by Catherine Petroski, "A Bride's Passage: Susan Hathorn's Year Under Sail" and "Beautiful My Mane in the Wind".
- Programs, 1910-2008
  The majority of this series consists of the Halcyon Literary Club program booklets, created each year with the annual theme, schedule, and lists of participating and hosting members. Other materials include written book reviews, essays, and poems from different events.
  - Miscellaneous Program Materials
    - List of topics (Box 2)
    - List of club topics, 1910-2010 (Box 8)
    - Papers and articles (Box 2)
    - Poems (Box 2)
    - Christmas music program recording, 2008; 1 CD containing 1 audio file, 17.4 MB (Digital-materials RL00492-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 1)
      1 audio file in WMA format
  - Program Booklets
    - Studies in Southern Literature, 1910-1911 (Box 2)
    - North Carolina: A Study in Social History and Resources, 1911-1912 (Box 2)
    - Mexico, 1912-1913 (Box 2)
    - Norway and Sweden, 1913-1914 (Box 2)
    - Famous Women, 1914-1915 (Box 2)
    - Italian Art, 1915-1916 (Box 2)
    - Seventeenth Century Art, 1916-1917 (Box 2)
    - Contemporary Literature, 1919-1920 (Box 2)
    - Contemporary Drama, 1920-1921 (Box 2)
    - American Life as Portrayed in American Fiction, 1921-1922 (Box 2)
    - South America, 1922-1923 (Box 2)
    - Music, 1923-1924 (Box 2)
    - Literature of Today, 1924-1925 (Box 2)
    - The Old North State: Past and Present, 1925-1926 (Box 2)
    - British Isles, 1926-1927 (Box 2)
    - Memoirs and Biography, 1927-1928, 1928-1929 (Box 2)
    - Our Own United States, 1929-1930 (Box 2)
    - Anniversary: Selected Topics, 1930-1931 (Box 2)
    - Short Stories and Short Story Writers, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
    - A Journey in Spain, 1932-1933 (Box 2)
    - Selected Topics, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
    - North America (United States, the Mixing Bowl), 1933-1934, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
    - Selected Topics, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
    - North Carolina, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
    - Modern Drama, 1938-1939 (Box 2)
    - Loafing through the Pacific: World Cruise, 1939-1940 (Box 2)
    - The Arts in Georgian England, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - Selected Topics, 1941-1942 (Box 3)
    - Book Reviews, 1942-1943 (Box 3)
    - Book Reviews, 1943-1944 (Box 3)
    - Selected Topics, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
    - Places and People of the Mediterranean, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
    - Rivers of America, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Famous Families, 1947-1948 (Box 3)
    - Famous Cities, 1948-1949 (Box 3)
    - Career Women at Mid-Century, 1949-1950 (Box 3)
    - Americans from Abroad, 1950-1951 (Box 3)
    - Humor and Humorists, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Other Peoples' Lives, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
    - Books of Travel, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
    - Book Reviews, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - Travel, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
    - The Great West; in Fact and Fiction, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
    - The Art Collection of the North Carolina Museum, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
    - Music, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    - Study of Theater (Various Countries), 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - Around the World, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Golden anniversary program, 1910-1960 (Box 8)
    - Cultural and Political Personalities of the Last Decade - 1950-1960, 1961-1962 (Box 3)
    - Book Reviews: Collector's Items, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
    - The Cabinet of the United States, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
    - From the Mountains to the Sea, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - Biographies and Autobiographies of Women, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
    - The Modern Arts, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - Great Castles and Palaces of the World, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Man and Religion, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Kaleidoscope, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Book Reviews, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - "Civilisation," by Kenneth Clark, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - NOW, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - A Year of Books, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - Women, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - Interesting Americans, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Any Subject, Book, or Person of Current Interest, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
    - Different Cultures of the World, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - Twentieth Century Fiction-Non Fiction, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Looking Back on the 70s: A Review of the Past Decade, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
    - Famous Families, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - North Carolina Personalities, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - The Life and Work of a Colorful Literary Personality, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - Famous Artists, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - Museums of Interest, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Kings, Queens, and Jacks, 1985-1986 (Box 4)
    - Famous Churches of the World, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Mysteries, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
    - Mistresses, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - American Dynasties, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - The Irish, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Focus on Your Favorite Author, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Book Review of 90s Best Seller, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Portraits of Ladies, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - The Joy of Music/A Variety of Religious Experiences, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
    - Saints and Sinners, 1995-1996 (Box 4)
    - Art and Design, 1996-1997 (Box 4)
    - Great Love Affairs, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - A New Generation of Southern Literatures; Our Contemporary NC Writers, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - The Greatest Generation: Milestones of the 20th Century, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
    - Heroes, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
    - Women who Made a Difference, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - Potpourri, 2002-2003 (Box 4)
    - Sacred Sites, 2003-2004 (Box 4)
    - Southern Comfort, 2004-2005 (Box 4)
    - "Books that Made a Difference" and Revised Edition, 2005-2006 (Box 4)
    - Journeys of Life, 2006-2007 (Box 4)
    - Dreams and Discoveries, 2008-2009 (Box 8)
    - 100 Years of Fashion and Music, 2010-2011 (Box 8)
- Club Administration, 1923-2011
  This series includes meeting minutes, copies of the constitution, financial records, and receipts from various charitable donations made by Halcyon. This series also includes notes from families across the world thanking the Halcyon Club for contributing Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe (C.A.R.E.) packages during the post-war period. Thematic summaries of the meeting minutes have been collected by Halcyon members and are included in the Club History Series.
  - Minutes
    - 1923-1926 (Box 5)
    - 1926-1932 and undated, by Susie Shipp (Box 5)
    - October 1931-November 1940, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1941-1952, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1952 (Box 5)
    - November 1952-May 1954 (Box 5)
    - 1954-1964 (Box 5)
    - 1964-November 1970 (Box 5)
    - December 1970-May 1972 (Box 5)
    - October 1972-December 1974, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - January 1975-May 1975 (Box 6)
    - October 1975-May 1976 (Box 6)
    - October 1976-January 1978 (Box 6)
    - February 1978-March 1979 (Box 6)
    - April 1979-December 1980 (Box 6)
    - January 1981-May 1982 (Box 6)
    - October 1982-May 1983 (Box 6)
    - October 1983-May 1985 (Box 6)
    - October 1985-May 1987 (Box 6)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 6)
    - October 1990-May 1991 (Box 6)
    - October 1991-May 1992 (Box 6)
    - October 1992-May 1993 (Box 6)
    - October 1993-May 1994 (Box 6)
    - October 1994-May 1995 (Box 6)
    - October 1995-May 1996 (Box 6)
    - October 1996-May 1997 (Box 6)
    - October 1999-May 2002 (Box 6)
    - 2002-2005, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - 2005-2007 (Box 7)
    - October 2007-May 2008 (Box 8)
    - October 2008- May 2009 (Box 8)
    - October 2009-May 2010 (Box 8)
    - October 2010-May 2011 (Box 8)
  - Financial and Administrative Materials
    - Treasurer's Records, 1934-2006, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Constitutions and Bylaws, 1931-2008 (Box 7)
    - 1947 Day Planner with notes about members (Box 7)
    - Receipts and thank you notes for charitable donations (Box 7)
    - Receipts and information about C.A.R.E. packages, 1950s-1961 (Box 7)
    - Thank you letters re: C.A.R.E. packages, 1948-1959 (Box 7)
    - Duke archive correspondence, club agreement, 2009-2011 (Box 8)
  - Special Events and Photographs
    - Event photographs, 2011 (Box 8)
    - Centennial Celebration Planning Committee, 2008-2009 (Box 8)
    - Centennial meetings recordings, 2010-2011; 1 CD containing 5 audio files, 167 MB (Digital-materials RL00492-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 1)
      5 audio files in WMA format
    - Luncheon photographs, 2011 May; 1 CD containing 30 files, 158 MB (Digital-materials RL00492-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 1)
      30 photograph files in JPG format